A Guide to the A Guide to the John Early Papers 1800-1856
Archives and Special Collections, McGraw-Page Library, Randolph-Macon College
Archives and Special Collections, McGraw-Page Library, Randolph-Macon College
The John Early Papers
Archives and Special Collections, McGraw-Page Library, Randolph-Macon College
Methodist Vertical File Early 1
The collection contains 63 folders in 6 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection is a combination of Randolph-Macon College materials, Virginia Conference materials and donated materials. Much of the collection was presented to the college by J. Rives Childs, October 1930, in connection with the celebration of the centennial of the college. Additional materials were donated in December 1945. Mr. Childs was the great-grandson of Bishop Early and a 1912 alumnus of the college. Other donors include Miss Fanny Early, Dr. L.R. Littleton and Frank J. Merryman.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born January 1, 1786 in Bedford County Virginia, the thirteenth child of Joshua and Mary Early, Bishop John Early joined the Methodist Church following his conversion in April of 1804. Licensed to preach after 1806 - 1807, he began his ministry at Poplar Forest in Bedford, Virginia ministering to Mr. Jefferson's slaves. By 1811, he was traveling the Greenville Circuit and received more than 500 persons into the church. A stirring preacher, he attracted the attention of church leaders and became a Presiding Elder in 1813. Although he held many important positions in the church he was not elected to the Episcopacy until 1854, due to his connection to slavery. In 1821 he married Elizabeth Rives. He was offered several positions in the federal government, which he declined, feeling they would be in opposition to his ministerial calling. He was instrumental in the local government of Lynchburg, VA, and supported various causes and enterprises, such as the James River and Kanawha Canal and the Viginia and Tennessee Railroad Company. He was also instrumental in the founding of Randolph-Macon College and served as President of the Board of Trustees for nearly 40 years, as well as serving as College Agent. He died on November 5, 1873 and is buried in Spring Hill Cemetary in Lynchburg, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The collection primarily contains information bearing on Randolph-Macon College and the Virginia Conference of the Methodist Church. Diaries cover 1807 to 1813. Correspondence beginning in 1800 includes family and other prominent Methodists (William McKendree and Leonidas Rosser). Methodist materials include General Conference information from 1830, 1836, 1840 and 1844, ordination certificates and sermon notes.
Arrangement
Correspondence is arranged chronologically by folder, other material is arranged by subject.
Contents List
- Diaries 1807-1813
  - Diary 1807 (Folder 6)
  - Diary 1808 (Folder 7)
  - Diary 1810, 2 volumes (Folder 8)
  - Diary 1811 (Folder 9)
  - Diary 1812 (Folder 10)
  - Diary 1813 (Folder 11)
- Administrative 1940 (Folder 5)
  - Administrative Correspondence 1940 (Folder 5)
  - Index (Folder 3)
  - Index (Folder 4)
- Narratives
  - Traveling Preacher, The Story of Bishop John Early by William K. Thomas 1964 (Folder 1)
  - An Account of the Experience and Travels of John Early from 25 May 1807-June 8,1814 Transcribed by Deborah Pugh 2002 (Folder 2)
  - Memorial Discourse 1873, 1 item (Folder 37)
    On the death of John Early delivered by Bishop Doggett
  - Portraits of John Early, 2 items (Folder 40)
  - Later Articles about John Early 1879-1972, 2 items (Folder 43)
  - Obituaries, 10 items (Folder 53)
  - Obituaries, 12 items (Folder 54)
  - Lynchburg Magazine Nov/Dec 1972, 1 item (Folder 55)
- Correspondence 1800-1874
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1800-1840, 13 items (Folder 12)
  - Correspondence of John Early and William McKendree 1821-1829, 8 items (Folder 13)
  - Corresponence of John Early and Elizabeth B. Early 1823-1857, 96 items (Folder 14)
  - Letters bearing on Randolph-Macon 1825, 1827, 2 items (Folder 15)
    - D. Dempsy to John Early, proposing Leaksville N.C. April 16, 1827
    - Gabriel Disoway to John Early, written on printed circular, Address to the Members and Friends of the Methodist Episcopal Church January 17, 1825
  - Correspondence of John Early and J. Emory 1829-1832, 6 items (Folder 16)
  - Letters bearing on Randolph-Macon College 1830-1831, 7 items (Folder 18)
  - Letters bearing on Randolph-Macon College 1832-1833, 22 items (Folder 19)
  - Correspondence of John Early and Eleazer Early 1833-1834, 9 items (Folder 20)
  - Letters Bearing on Randolph-Macon College 1834-1835, 29 items (Folder 21)
  - Letters Bearing on Randolph-Macon College 1836-1837, 10 items (Folder 23)
  - Letters Bearing on Randolph-Macon College 1838-1839, 15 items (Folder 24)
  - Letters Bearing on Randolph-Macon College 1840, 16 items (Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1841-1846, 12 items (Folder 26)
  - Letters Bearing on Randolph-Macon College 1841-1861, 41 items (Folder 28)
  - Correspondence of John Early 1847-1850, 22 items (Folder 30)
  - Correspondence of Thomas Early (son of John Early) 1850-1894, 18 items (Folder 32)
  - Correspondence of John Early 1851-1856, 5 items (Folder 33)
  - John Early - Leonida Rosser Correspondence 1853-1854, 4 items (Folder 34)
    given by Dr. l. R. Littleton
  - Miscellaneoud Correspondence 1861-1874, 9 items (Folder 36)
  - Envelopes, 6 items (Folder 38)
  - Letters and Papers Bearing on Randolph-Macon College, 13 items (Folder 49)
    Given by Miss Fanny Early
  - Correspondence 1857-1860, 13 items (Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, 60 items (Folder 4-2)
- Methodist Materials 1830-1849
  - Minutes of the Annual Conferences of the Methodist Episcopal Church 1830 (Folder 17)
  - General Conference 1836, 1 item (Folder 22)
  - Appointment Book- Lynchburg 1841-1844, 2 volumes (Folder 27)
  - Pamphlets -Church Engaging in Merchandise 1849 (Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous items, 45 items (Folder 44)
  - Methodist Episcopal Church, South Conference, miscellaneous papers (Folder 3-2)
- Randolph-Macon Material
  - Promissory Note 1846 (Folder 29)
  - Subscriptions to the College, 40 items (Folder 41)
  - Collections to Endorse a Professorship in R.M. College 1838 (Drawer 2)
  - Account Books of RMC Agent Jn. Early 1833-1838
- Family/Personal Material 1822-1857
  - Papers concerning Thomas Early 1859, 4 items (Folder 35)
    include Deacon's Orders,1859
  - Confederate Materials, 10 items (Folder 39)
  - Sermon Notes, 3 volumes (Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 47 items (Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 21 items (Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 19 items (Folder 27)
    Includes "On Baptism" and information on Spring Hill Cemetery
  - Personal Papers, 11 items (Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 12 items (Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous Items, 4 items (Folder 51)
  - Day Book 1822 (Folder 1-2)
  - Executor's Account (Thomas H. Early) (Folder 2-2)